[Music]
Welcome to this what's new about all the
AL language changes we've done in this
2025 release wave 2.
I'm going to walk you through some of
the changes that we've done in this
release. And if you are interested in
jumping to some of the details, you can
look at the description below to find
the thing that interests you the most.
As always, I like to start with code. So
let's go to my code space here and take
a look at a table I created. The first
thing I want to draw your attention to
is the allowing customizations. This is
not a new property, but we've had to
change it a little bit to be more
flexible. So we deprecated the always
option and extended it with two new as
read only as read write. Whereas the as
read only is the same as always. We also
added the to be classified option in
order for you to specify that you're not
quite done with this classification.
In this table here, I have different
kinds of fields. Some of them are as
read only. Some of them might be to be
classified. Others may have the never
option as you might have seen before and
one has the new one as readrite.
I also have a page on it where I have
all these fields in my page. If I want
to create a customization on this page,
I can then go and edit it. If I try to
then make the entry number read or
writable, then because it's read only,
I'll get an error. So, I cannot make it
editable. The same goes for the field
that has the to be classified option. It
can also not be made editable.
The description field which has the as
read write can be made editable on my
page customization here. And of course
as before if you specified never you
cannot use that field in a page
customization.
Going back to my table here let's look
at some of the other things we have in
here. We have a new property on fields
called mask type. The mask type has two
options for now. The none and the
concealed. The idea here is that you
will specify the mask type if you want
to conceal some data from the UI. Not to
be confused with the extended data type
masked because that has a very different
behavior in the UI. We'll see that in a
little while. On the extended data
types, we added a new option called
document. Document is intended for you
to to tell the client that this media is
actually a document and should be
rendered in portrait mode. We'll also
see that in a little while. For the
existing properties, auto format type
and auto format expression, we added a
new code cup rule that will help you
enforce the usage of these properties.
Using these properties will help models
understand what kind of data needs to go
into these fields.
Okay, let's go back to my page here on
this table. As you can see, I have added
the fields here. And I want to draw your
attention to an existing feature that
you might want to use, which is the code
action to move the tool tips to the
table for that reuse across multiple
pages. On this page, we talked about the
fields that had the mask type concealed.
One of them being the sensitive code,
another one being the masked amount. I
also added here a custom field pin code
that is actually using the extended data
type masked. So we can see in a second
the difference between these two
properties
on my page here. I also added some fact
boxes. The first fact box is the summary
fact box. You don't need to add the
summary fact box on your pages. They are
automatically added on the card list
plus and document pages. But if you want
to hide the summary page, summary fact
box, then you can add the system part by
referencing the summary system part and
set the visibility to false. This could
be a case where you have a card page
that does not need summarization. For
example, a setup page. I also added a
factbox here for my document so I can
get it rendered on the right in that
portrait mode. But let's go see it.
So here I have my page. On the left side
we have the fields and we'll see the
mask type concealed show up as dots here
and I can click the icon here to reveal
the data and hide it again. The same
goes for the decimal here. I can reveal
the data and hide it again. Remember the
pin code was extended data type masked.
So it has a different behavior. We don't
see any icon out here to begin with. If
I enter data, let's say 1 2 3 4, I can
reveal this data and I can hide it
again. But as soon as I step out of this
field, I'm done editing it, the option
to reveal it again disappears. So
there's a very different behavior
between the mask type concealed and the
extended data type masked.
On the right side here, we see the
summary. I haven't started summarizing
yet. You can go try it out yourself. If
I wanted to hide it, I would set the
visibility.
Below this one, we see the flight
document. As you can see here, it's
rendered in portrait mode, giving me a
good view that this is actually a
document and not just an image.
Let's go back to code on reports. We
added the ability to specify tool tips.
Tool tips can give you extra data in
your report that will help the users
know what this data is about. And the
tool tip will actually be part of the
XML data that's in your Word report or
Excel report. So let's go check it out.
I have a report here. I can preview it.
In this report, I added the tool tip.
And as you can see here, let's zoom in a
little bit.
I have the field of the column name here
and I have the value, but I also have
the tool tip over here. So now you can
add instructions into your report using
the tool tips.
Let's go back to code here. If you work
with a lot of data here, you have now a
new option to use the truncate method on
tables. The truncate method is more
performant but also has some
limitations. Among others, you cannot
use it on media tables. I recommend
everyone who thinks about using it to go
check out the documentation about all
the places where you can use it and
where you cannot use it.
If you work with locks, you might find
this new method very useful. You can set
the lock timeout duration to a certain
number of milliseconds. You can also set
it to zero, meaning disabling it if you
want to. Of course, I do not recommend
that as it would wait indefinitely.
If you work with record refs, you might
find it easy now to use field names to
access the fields. You can use the new
field exists in order to check whether a
field exists in the record ref. And you
can use the field name in the fields
collection here to get to the value of
it.
If you work with grids in keys and
indexes, you might find that they're not
that performant. You can now use the
create sequential GUID to get a GUID
that is not quite fully random. This
will help in the performance when
inserting a lot of GIDs in indexes.
If you work with data transfer objects,
you can now use the update audit fields
property and set it to false if you do
not want the audit fields to be updated
when you use the copy fields function.
We noticed that the text constant did
not have all the text methods that you
would come to expect from text variables
in AL. So now we added them. So now you
have all the different text manipulation
methods that you would expect from a
text variable.
Let's see. Here we go. Contains ends
with index of and so forth.
Making it look like a real text variable
in AL.
Let's undo that. There we go. Record ID
changed a bit in this release.
If you format a record ID, you will get
the flight data, the table name or the
flight log entry, the table name using
the format zero. If you use format one,
you will still get the caption of that
table and of course the key. But now if
you use format two or format 9, you will
get the fully qualified name of a table
that is namespaced.
In this case, we have two tables. The
flight data is not namespaced. So
therefore there is not a namespace in
this format here but the flight lock
entry is namespaced. So you get a fully
qualified name as you can see here for
that table.
If you evaluate a record ID you can use
the fully qualified name here in order
to get that record ID. But you can also
use the backup option here of just the
name. We will try to retrieve the table
based on the name if we do not find the
fully qualified name.
As part of the namespace work, we also
introduce the AL namespace colum in the
metadata tables.
As you can see here, you can search for
a namespace and find that one table we
saw before that is currently namespaced
in this project.
from something new to something old. If
you want to deprecate an external
business event, this is now possible.
And as always, we recommend you change
the external display name so everybody
else outside of Business Central can see
that this business event is obsolete.
We also made it possible for you to
obsolete user controls using the
existing obsolete methods and
properties. Here for tests, we added a
new test type AI test. This is to
indicate that this test is all about
validating AI behaviors. We also added
the required test isolation property in
order for you to indicate to the users
of this code unit what kind of isolation
level you need to run the tests in this
code unit. If you choose to run the
tests in a different kind of isolation
level, they might not work for you.
These are the changes that we have had
in this release.
Before I leave you, I just want to show
you one small addition that we did to
the VS Code extension. I have here an
install code unit and you can read it
and see if you can find the error. If I
do a publish,
we'll find that the publish
will take quite a long time and
sometimes we know that there's an error
in here and it will never ever complete.
We've now taken the cancellation token
here and propagated it all the way to
the server. So when I click cancel the
whole operation
will stop.
This should help those of you out there
who've had challenges with publishing
and having never ending publish
operations
uh whenever you're using VS Code. That's
it for me. I hope you enjoyed this short
walkrough of all the language features
that was changed in this release. Thank
you very much.